[English subtitles are available]
[본 영상은 한글자막을 제공합니다]
[The Science of Falling in Love]
[이과생추입정망 : 사랑의 늪에 빠진 이과생]
[Episode 11]
[제11화]
Come on, Su Chengcheng.
쑤청청
Let out all your anger
요 며칠 동안의 분노를
from the past few days!
한 번 해소해 봐
Are you playing coquettish?
지금 애교 부리는 거야?
Harder!
더 세게
One more time!
한 번 더
One, two!
하나, 둘
I...
저...
One more time!
한 번 더
One, two!
하나, 둘
Hit it!
때려
One more time!
한 번 더
Use your leg!
발차기
Good job!
잘했어
You feel good?
이제 기분 좀 풀려?
Yes.
기분이 좋아요
I feel like I can do it again.
다시 살아난 것 같아요
Okay.
그럼
Do you want to stay?
가지 말고 계속 있는 것 어때?
Stay?
가지...
Stay
가지 않고
and follow Xiao Yuhe
샤오위허랑 같이 일하라고요?
or
우리 팀에
come to my group.
들어와도 되고
Follow you?
선배 팀이요?
You don't want to?
싫어?
It’s okay.
괜찮아
Anyway, the NSF program
국가자연기금 프로젝트에 참여하면
have extra credits,
학점을 추가로 받을 수 있을 뿐만 아니라
which are helpful for getting postgraduate recommendation and going abroad.
대학원 진학과 해외 유학에도 도움이 되지
And
그리고
there are also creative credits.
창신 학점도 받을 수 있어서
I think there are other students
들어오려는 친구
who want to join us.
많을 거야
I don't force you.
강요하진 않을게
I...
저...
I want to come.
저도 들어가고 싶어요
Thank you, Senior Xixi.
고마워요, 선배
No need to thank me.
고맙긴
See you in the lab.
그럼 실험실에서 보자
When can I
나도 언제면
be as handsome as Senior Xixi?
시시 선배처럼 멋있어질 수 있을까?
It's done.
네 말대로 했으니까
Don't forget what you promised me.
나랑 한 약속 잊지 마
Okay.
그래
Chengcheng, what are you doing?
청청, 뭐 하는 거야?
Packing up my things
짐 정리하고
to go back to the lab.
실험실에 돌아가려고
Didn't you fail to change the lab?
실험실 변경에 실패했다고 하지 않았어?
She didn't change it.
변경하지 않았어
She's still in the same lab.
전에 있던 실험실에 가는 거야
What about Xiao Yuhe?
너랑 샤오위허
Didn't you and he already
싸워서
have a standoff?
어색하지 않아?
Even if I go back,
돌아가도
I won't be in his group.
그 사람이랑 한 팀이 되진 않을 거야
I'll go to Senior Xixi's group.
난 시시 선배 팀에 들어갈 거야
Now,
나도
I’ve gotten over it.
생각해 봤는데
Xiao Yuhe
샤오위허 같은
such a small trouble
사람 때문에
is not even
신경 쓸
in my consideration.
필요 없어
When I see him now,
앞으로 샤오위허를
I just
보면
ignore him.
그냥 무시할 거야
That's good.
잘됐네
I heard that
시시 선배가
Senior Xixi's research
생쥐의 행동에 관한
is mainly about
뉴로모픽 분석과 식별을
EEG analysis and recognition of mouse behavior.
연구한다고 들었는데
If you
너도 옆에서
study with her,
배울 게
you'll definitely improve a lot.
많을 거야
I looked it up.
내가 한 번 알아봤는데
There are a lot of English in this area.
영어 자료를 많이 봐야 한대
Aren't you preparing for IELTS?
너 요즘 아이엘츠 준비하고 있으니까
You must have a very large vocabulary.
영어 단어 많이 알고 있지?
If I don’t know anything,
나중에 모르는 거 있으면
I will ask you.
너한테 물어볼게
Anyway, in the future,
아무튼
I no longer have to
앞으로 다시는
follow Xiao Yuhe
샤오위허랑 같이
to collect data and run data.
데이터 만들고 분석할 필요가 없어
Mice, I'm coming.
생쥐들, 기다려
Sitting here again?
여기 있었네
Isn't this the jacket
이건 청청이
that Chengcheng bought for you?
너한테 사 준 옷 아니야?
It’s new, why did you dry clean it?
새 옷인데 왜 드라이 워시했어?
Because someone I don't like
제가 싫어하는 사람이
tried it on.
입어 봐서요
Xiao,
위허
as your senior,
선배로서
I have to enlighten you.
너한테 좀 말해줘야겠다
You are
넌 뭐든
usually good at everything,
다 좋은데
but you are too boring.
너무 답답해
I think that
내가 볼 땐
you are a typical
넌 애정 결핍증이
lack of security.
있어
I've read a paper before
전에 논문에서 봤는데
which is about the people who are quite similar to you.
너랑 비슷한 것 같아
It’s said that
사랑받고 싶으면서도
there is a type of people
상대방이
who want to be loved,
다가오면
but when others
또 거리를 두고
respond to you,
상대방이 거리를 두면
you reject them.
또 버림받기
When others reject you,
싫어하는
you don’t want to be abandoned.
사람도 있대
You are
이건 모순되는
contradicting yourself.
심리 아니야?
Take the case
너랑 쑤청청의 일을
between you and Su Chengcheng before.
예시로 들어볼게
You are the one
네가 청청을 돕고 싶어서
who helped her clean the data.
데이터를 분석해 줬는데
But
걔한테
you didn't even tell her.
말하지도 않았잖아
To help her change the lab,
실험실 변경해 주려고
you did a lot of work,
그렇게 애썼는데도
but you still didn’t tell her,
걔한테 말해주지 않아서
which blew it all up.
결국 난장판이 됐잖아
Well,
너 자꾸
you can't always act like
도와줬는데
I'm helping you,
말해주지는 않고
but I won't tell you.
그냥 내 마음이야
Just for fun.
이런 태도로 사람을 대하면
How... how can you
상대방이
let others understand you?
네 마음을 알 수 있겠어?
Right?
안 그래?
Express yourself truthfully
청청한테 네 마음을
to Chengcheng.
표현해
It's not that hard.
그거 어려운 일 아니야
Good morning, everyone.
여러분, 좋은 아침이에요
Good morning, Chengcheng.
- 좋은 아침 - 청청
You're back.
돌아왔네?
Yes.
그러니까
Senior Jiafa,
자파 선배
I bought you some milk tea.
제가 밀크티 사 왔어요
As soon as Chengcheng comes back,
청청 후배가 돌아오니까
my treatment
나도 다시
comes back.
덕을 보게 되네
Senior Dongmao,
동마오 선배
my gift for you
이건
is a wired headset.
유선 이어폰이에요
Thank you.
고마워
Nothing.
아니에요
This is good.
이거 좋네
Senior Zhang Li,
장리 선배
this packet of pumpkin seeds is for you.
이건 호박씨예요
It's a local specialty,
특산물이라
which is hard to buy.
사기 힘든 건데
And it has thin skin and thick flesh.
껍질이 얇고 과육이 많아서
It's delicious. Try it.
맛있어요, 한 번 드셔보세요
Okay, thank you, Chengcheng.
그래, 고마워, 청청
Nothing.
고맙긴요
Senior,
선배
this hand cream
이건 빵 냄새가 나는
is bread scented. It smells good.
핸드크림이에요
After applying it,
바르면
you'll look lovely.
사람이 러블리해져요
I think it suits you.
선배한테 잘 어울리는 것 같아요
How can a hand cream
핸드크림에서
smell like bread?
빵 냄새가 난다고?
Rum cheese flavor.
데킬라 치즈 향이 나네
It smells good.
향 너무 좋다
Right?
향 좋죠?
Thank you.
고마워
You're welcome.
아니에요
Senior Xixi,
시시 선배
this hand brewed coffee,
이건 핸드 드립 커피예요
I bought it for you.
선배 주려고 샀어요
I don't need it.
난 필요 없어
After being a butterfly,
선물 다 돌렸으면
come to the lab later.
이따 실험 데스크 쪽으로 와
Are you comfortable?
앉아 있으니까 편하지?
Catch it.
빨리 시작해
Senior,
선배
after I catch it,
이걸 잡고
then what should I do?
뭘 하면 돼요?
First anesthetize it,
마취부터 하고
then position it in three dimensions
자리를 고정해 줘
and disinfect its head.
그리고 머리에 있는 털을 제모하고 소독한 다음
Cut a small opening
작은 상처를 내고
and use a dental drill to make a hole.
발치겸자로 구멍을 내
Scared?
못 하겠어?
It doesn’t matter.
괜찮아
I had a graduate student
전에도 대학원생 중에
who also didn't dare to do it.
못 하겠다는 학생이 있어서
Then Pro. Du sent him
두 교수님이
to medical school
의학원에 보내서
to kill mice for two years. Then...
2년 동안 생쥐를 죽이게 했지
Well,
어때?
let me send you there too?
너도 거기로 보내줄까?
To learn about behavioral therapy.
이걸 행동 요법이라고 하지
No, no, no.
아니요
I... I can do it.
저... 저 할 수 있어요
Hello,
손님
what ingredients do you want?
밀크티에 추가하고 싶은 거 있어요?
Pearls, taro balls...
펄, 타로볼
All of them.
뭐든 다 넣어주세요
Are you sure?
다 넣는 거
All ingredients?
확실해요?
Yes.
네
Okay.
알겠습니다
Hello,
손님
your ingredients are a little too much
추가한 게 많다 보니
for our cups.
용량이 부족해서
I use an extra-large cup.
점보 사이즈로 바꿨어요
Take it.
여기요
Thank you.
고마워요
Chengcheng.
청청
Gu Chen, why are you here?
구천, 무슨 일이야?
Last time I did the experiment,
저번에 한 실험이
and found it really interesting,
재밌어서
so I applied to the school
학교에 신청했더니
to transfer over.
여기로 변경해 줬어
Senior Xixi is not here?
시시 선배는 여기 없어?
She just went out for something.
아까 바쁘다고 나갔어
Did you apply
신청만 했는데
and transfer here directly?
여기로 변경해 준 거야?
What's your GPA?
너 학점이 얼마야?
4.9.
4.9
Sure enough,
역시
opportunities are always reserved
기회는 다 학점의 신한테
for those who have a good GPA.
주는 거구나
Chengcheng,
청청
are you going to
너 지금 생쥐 몸 안에
implant electrodes in mice?
전극을 넣으려는 거야?
You need to prepare the skin first,
일단 껍질을 준비하고
and then fix it with a brain stereotaxic.
뇌정위 고정장치로 고정해야 해
Well,
아니면
let me show you how to do it.
내가 시범으로 보여줄게
Come on, you do it.
그래, 그래
Gu Chen, you are really my savior.
구천, 넌 정말 내 생명의 은인이야
After removing the hair here,
여기를 제모하고
make an incision
이 틈을 따라
along this sagittal suture,
상처를 낸 다음
and then peel the fascia and muscle
두개골 위에 있는 근막과
from the skull.
근육을 분리해야 해
I don't see any hydrogen peroxide here.
과산화수소수가 없는 것 같은데
Go and get one.
하나 가져다줘
Okay.
그래
Hello, Senior Xiao.
샤오 선배, 안녕하세요
What are you doing here?
여기서 뭐 하는 거야?
I applied to be transferred
제가 선배 실험실로
to our lab.
소속 변경했어요
I've already told Du Zhuanjia.
두프로한테도 얘기했는데
He said I'll follow you in the future.
앞으로 선배 밑에서 배우면 된대요
If you need anything,
앞으로 필요한 거 있으면
just tell me.
저한테 얘기하세요
Gu Chen,
구천
in fact, you can can learn more things
사실 시시 선배 팀에 들어가면
in Senior Xixi's group.
배울 게 더 많은데
Why don't you tell the teacher
우리 팀에 들어오겠다고
to transfer to our group?
교수님한테 얘기해 보는 건 어때?
Gu Chen,
구천
please
그럼 생쥐들이 쓸
go and change the padding for the mice first.
패킹 좀 바꿔 줘
Okay.
네
Wait.
잠깐만요
Gu Chen hasn't decided
구천이 선배 팀에 들어갈진
to go to your group yet,
아직 결정 나지 않았어요
why are you asking him to do that?
벌써 심부름시키면 안 되죠
Besides,
그리고
the mice are the business of our group,
생쥐는 저희 팀의 연구 과제라서
it's not your business.
선배가 신경 쓸 일은 아니죠
I don't think
패킹 바꾸는 건
he needs to change the padding.
구천한테 시킬 필요 없잖아요
He has already said that
걔가 말했잖아
he is under my charge.
내 밑에서 일하겠다고
So
그러니까
he has to do
내 말
whatever I tell him to do.
들어야지
Please go and change the padding.
패킹 좀 바꿔줘
Okay.
네
It's okay, Chengcheng.
괜찮아, 청청
I'll go change it.
내가 가서 할게
Inexplicable.
하여튼 이상한 사람이야
I need to collect
수면 중인 생쥐의
EEG data from the olfactory layer
후각층 ERP가 어떻게 되는지
of mice during sleep.
데이터를 수집해야 해
Cooperate with me.
협조해 줘
Sorry,
죄송해요
I'm not very good at it.
전 그런 거 잘 못해요
Aren't you a whiz?
선배는 능력자잖아요
You can do it yourself.
직접 하세요
Fine.
그래
Someone else is good at it.
네가 못 해도 잘하는 사람은 있어
I'll tell Zhang Xixi later that
이따 장시시한테 얘기할 거야
you don't cooperate with me,
네가 협조하지 않아서
and let her cooperate with me herself.
걔가 해줘야 할 것 같다고
I go with you.
갈게요
I can't send it off.
못 줬네
Senior Xiao,
샤오 선배
I've changed it.
다 바꿨어요
Prof. Wang has a data,
왕 교수님한테 가서
go to get it.
데이터 자료 갖고 와
I just ran into Senior Dongmao
아까 동마오 선배
on the way.
봤는데
He also told me about it.
동마오 선배도 그 말 해서
So I got it back
가는 김에
on the way to change the padding.
갖고 왔어요
Our lab
우리 실험실에서
has opened a new experiment
새로운 분야를 연구하고 있는데
related to neural pathway damage
골수 손상으로 인한
in spinal cord injury.
신경 손상과 관한 거야
Gather some information
가서 자료 검색해 보고
and write a literature review.
논문 작성해 봐
When I first transferred to the lab,
실험실에 온 지 얼마 안 됐을 때
I talked with Prof. Du about this topic,
두 교수님과도 이 얘기를
and he also told me about it.
나눈 적이 있어요
So,
그래서
I made some preparations in advance.
미리 준비해 봤어요
Look, Senior Xiao,
보고 또 필요한 게
if there's not enough,
있으면
I'll find more.
더 알아볼게요
Gu Chen, are you done?
구천, 다 바꿨어?
Whose milk tea?
누구 밀크티예요?
Who knows?
그러니까
Yuhe,
위허
didn't you
그거 네가
just bring it here yourself?
가져온 거 아니야?
Someone
전엔 누가 그랬더라?
said before that
건강한 성인의 일평균
the daily caffeine intake
카페인 섭취량이
of a healthy adult
200mg을
should not exceed 200 milligrams.
초과하면 안 된다고
But the caffeine content
그런데 밀크티의
of milk tea
카페인 함량은
is 300 milligrams.
300mg이라서
In order to get a good sleep,
수면의 질을 위해
he never drinks milk tea.
종래로 밀크티를 마시지 않는다고
This is the one I often drink.
제가 자주 가는 가게 거네요
I have to
오늘
experiment late today,
늦게까지 실험할 것 같아서
so I bought a cup on the way.
오는 김에 산 거야
Such a big cup.
이렇게 큰 거로요?
Stay up all night?
밤새우려는 거예요?
Why don't you drink it?
왜 아직도 안 마셔요?
I ate too much this morning,
아침에 너무 배부르게 먹어서
I couldn't drink it.
못 마시겠어
I'll see if you drink it later.
이따 마시나 한번 보겠어요
When I drink it is none of your business.
언제 마시든 너랑 무슨 상관이야?
Who cares when you drink?
누가 신경 쓴대요?
I will drink it
언제 마실지는
whenever I want.
내 마음이야
I don’t care.
마시든 말든 저랑 상관없어요
I want to drink now, I drink now.
난 지금 당장 마실 수도 있어
Drink it.
그럼 마셔요
Fine.
누가 못 마실까 봐?
Delicious.
맛있어
Annoying!
짜증 나
Gu Chen, have you eaten?
구천, 밥 먹었어?
No.
아니
Let's go eat.
같이 밥 먹으러 가자
Okay.
그래
Our counselor
선생님 말이야
is very strict with us.
너무 엄격해
What's wrong?
왜 그래?
I feel like someone is following me.
누가 자꾸 따라오는 것 같아
I don't think so.
아닌데
You're looking at it wrong.
잘못 본 거 아니야?
Yuhe,
위허
where are we going to eat?
대체 어디서 먹을 거야?
We're almost done.
한 바퀴 다 돌았는데
I want to eat something spicy.
매운 거 먹고 싶어요
Let's find a heavy one.
자극적인 거 있는지 찾아봐요
Spicy. We just
매운 거?
passed a skewer store.
아까 꼬치집 하나 있었는데
Isn't it...
거기
Isn't it quite good?
맛있잖아
Yes.
그렇죠
Hey, hey!
여보세요?
Maybe it's a mistake.
아닌가 보네
Let's go.
가자
Nothing.
아니네요
I thought someone was calling.
전화 온 줄 알았어요
What's wrong with you?
너 왜 그래?
Nothing. Nothing.
아무것도 아니에요
We're lost.
여기가 어디야?
Just find one to eat.
얼른 아무 데나 들어가자
Come on, let's eat there.
저쪽에 가요
Let's go.
가요
What do you want to eat?
뭐 먹을래?
I heard that
여기 무화과 퀴노아 샐러드가
their fig and quinoa salad is very popular.
맛있대
[Light Salad]
[라이트 샐러드]
We can order one to try.
한번 먹어볼까?
Okay.
좋아
Here's your order.
여기 영수증이요
Please wait for a moment.
잠시만 기다려 주세요
Hello,
안녕하세요
I'd like
무화과
one quinoa fig salad.
퀴노아 샐러드 하나요
And one...
그리고
Wait a moment, let me take a look.
잠시만요
Hello, Senior.
선배
You order.
먼저 주문하세요
Thank you.
고마워
Why are you cutting in line?
왜 새치기하는 거예요?
I’d like one classic salad.
클래식 샐러드 하나요
Childish.
유치하긴
Wait a minute.
잠시만요
Thank you.
고마워요
Senior Xiao,
샤오 선배
sit here.
앉으세요
No need.
괜찮아
Sit here.
네가 앉아
Senior Jiafa, sit here.
자파 선배, 앉으세요
It’s okay. Thank you.
괜찮아, 괜찮아, 고마워
Have a seat.
앉아요
Thank you.
고마워
Do you have to
꼭 우리랑
share a table with us?
같은 테이블에 앉아야겠어요?
This is a public area.
여긴 공공 구역이야
It’s so late.
지금 몇 시인데
Why isn't the food served yet?
주문한 거 왜 아직도 안 나오지?
Hello. Here's your salad.
샐러드 나왔습니다
Thank you.
고마워요
Yuhe,
위허
don't you want to eat something spicy,
매운 거 먹겠다며?
and heavy?
자극적인 거 먹겠다며?
You ordered me a plate of green vegetables,
풀때기만 시킨 거야?
even without a piece of meat?
고기 하나 없이
You have high blood fat, high blood pressure
선배 요즘 고혈지에 고혈압
and high uric acid recently.
고요산인데
Don’t eat meat.
고기 먹으면 어떡해요?
I...
나...
What a party!
다들 여기 있었네
Meizi, you come today...
메이쯔, 너 오늘...
Sit here.
여기 앉아
I’ll pack it up to see the counselor.
난 포장하고 선생님 만나러 가야 해서
Okay.
그래
Sit here.
여기 앉아
Bye bye.
갈게요
Chengcheng,
청청
you come here often, right?
너 여기 자주 오지?
Yuhe and I chose for a long...
나랑 위허가 한참...
Xiao Yuhe,
샤오위허
you were going to the cafeteria, right?
식당에 가려고 했던 거 아니에요?
Don't you want to eat meat
고기랑 매운 거
and spicy food?
먹고 싶다면서요?
-This is a public area. - Take it.
- 여긴 공공 구역이야 - 선배를...
By the way, Chengcheng,
참, 청청
you’re following
너 지금 생쥐 실험
to do the mouse experiment now.
하고 있지?
Senior Xixi posted a paper
시시 선배가
on the repair
생쥐 골수 손상 회복에 관한
of spinal cord injury in mice.
논문을 발표했는데
I think it is particularly useful.
유용한 것 같아
You can read it.
너도 한번 봐봐
Which one?
어느 논문?
I even collected it today.
오늘 저장했는데
This one.
이거야
Gu Chen,
구천
there is some equipment in the lab
실험실에 비용 청구해야 할
that needs to be reimbursed.
장비들이 있는데
Take the invoices
네가 영수증 들고
to find Dongmao.
동마오한테 가 봐
Okay.
네
Chengcheng,
청청
I’m leaving now.
그럼 먼저 가볼게
I'll send you the paper on WeChat.
논문은 위챗으로 보낼게
Okay.
그래
He's been
온종일 날 괴롭힐
picking on me all day,
생각만 하고 있네
Don't know what he's thinking now.
지금은 또 무슨 생각하는 거야?
Su Chengcheng,
쑤청청
the data you gave me
네가 준 데이터를 보면
is too noisy.
소음이 너무 커
The signal-to-noise ratio is lower than 85 db.
신호 대 잡음비가 85데시벨보다 작아
The electrodes must not
전극이 삽입된 위치가
have been implanted in the right place.
잘못된 게 분명해
Redo this data.
가서 다시 해
This data can't be wrong.
그럴 리가 없어요
I’ve checked it many times.
제가 여러 번 확인해 봤거든요
You may not have checked it correctly.
네가 확인했다고 다 맞는 건 아니야
I don't care about you.
대화하기도 싫다
I've already switched to another group,
다른 팀에 갔는데도
but you're still tormenting me.
계속 날 괴롭히는 거야?
You asked me
생쥐를 대상으로
to do EEG experiments on mice,
ERP 실험을 하라고 하지 않나
and then you said
데이터가
the data from EEG experiments are not good,
잘못돼서 다시 하라고
and asked me to do it again.
하지 않나
I can’t do it.
계속 비난만 했지
If you can, do it yourself!
미덥지 않으면 본인이 직접 하든가
Senior Chengcheng,
청청 후배
Yuhe asked you to do mice experiments?
위허가 너한테 생쥐 실험을 하라고 했어?
Actually Yuhe...
사실 위허는...
In fact,
너한테 말하면
I should not tell you this.
안 되지만
But you are new here.
너도 온 지 얼마 안 됐으니까
Yuhe is afraid of mice.
사실 위허가 생쥐를 무서워해
Really?
설마요
He has high self-esteem,
걔도 자존심이 있는 거지
so we don't usually talk about it.
그래서 우리도 모른 척하고 있어
He works in the lab.
실험실에서 일하는데
How can he be afraid of mice?
생쥐를 무서워하다니요?
There are all kinds of fishes...
세상은 넓고 별의별...
Well,
아니
all ordinary people
사람은
have some shortcomings.
다 단점이 있으니까
Don't tell him that I told you that.
내가 말했다고 하지 마
Be afraid of mice.
생쥐를 무서워한다고?
Speechless.
어이없
Senior,
선배
I just thought about it.
아까 생각해 봤는데
My attitude is not right.
제 태도에도 문제가 있었던 것 같아요
So I’m here to apologize to you.
그래서 사과하려고요
So
저한테
can you
시범으로
show me how to do it?
한 번 더 보여줄 수 있어요?
I promise
다시는
I won't make the same mistake
같은 실수를
next time.
범하지 않을게요
Your apology...
사과를...
No need.
됐어
You just do it.
네가 직접 해
I'll check the quality of the data later.
내가 이따 데이터 봐줄게
No, Senior,
그러지 말고요, 선배
show it to me,
시범으로 보여주면
then I can learn with you.
제가 그대로 할게요
No need.
그럴 필요 없어
Senior,
선배
I'm really
제 실험 절차에
afraid of making mistakes
오류가 생길까 봐
in my experiments.
무서워서 그래요
Please show me once.
한 번만 해줘요
Why are you hiding?
왜 피해요?
Senior, why is your face white?
근데 얼굴이 왜 하얗게 질려 있어요?
Are you afraid of mice?
설마 생쥐를 무서워하는 건 아니죠?
How could I be afraid?
그럴 리가
I’ll just do it once.
그럼 딱 한 번만이야
Take it.
들고 있어요
Let me open it for you.
제가 열어줄게요
No need.
그럴 필요 없어
Oh my God!
세상에
Senior Xiao Yuhe
샤오위허 선배가
has let the mice go.
생쥐들을 풀어줬어요
Why are you so loud?
꼭 그렇게 크게 말해야 해?
I heard that
위허가
Yuhe let the mouse go.
생쥐들을 풀어줬다며?
Yes.
맞아요
I saw that.
제가 봤어요
Really?
안 돼
If Prof. Du knows that,
두 교수님이 알면
he must be furious.
화내실 텐데
Yes.
그러니까
He'll be furious.
화나시겠죠?
So many potato chips and drinks
고수 맛 감자칩과 음료가
flavored with cilantro.
왜 이렇게 많아?
Did Senior Xi buy them?
시시 누나가 산 건가?
I don't think so.
아닐 거야
I saw that Gu Chen
전에 구천이
brought a box of them when he came up today.
박스를 하나 들고 올라오던데
Chengcheng,
청청
someone is here for you.
누가 널 찾아
Why didn't you answer the phone?
전화는 왜 안 받아?
Where's your phone?
전화 안 갖고 왔어?
I have a big gossip
마침 빅뉴스가 있어서
to tell you.
너한테 말해 주려고
Hurry up! Let’s go.
빨리 따라 와
Chengcheng’s friend,
친구
there are no outsiders here.
우린 다 한 집 식구니까
If it's convenient,
같이
let's gossip together.
얘기해 보면 어때?
It seems a bit...
그건 좀...
It's not appropriate.
그건 좀 아니지 않아요?
Sit down.
앉아요
I'll sit down then.
그럼 앉을게요
This matter
사실
has to start with you.
너랑 관련된 얘기야
Do you remember that
저번에 너한테
the teacher who let you change the lab last time
실험실 옮기라던 교수님 이름이
named Jiang Songrui?
장쑹루이지?
I now know that
나 방금 알았는데
he is a superb person
그 교수님은
who loves to exploit students.
학생들을 엄청 부려 먹어
Do you know
그 교수님 실험실에서
the time clock for their lab?
다들 출결 언제 하는지 알아?
Do you know?
아세요?
007.
주 7일, 0시와 12시
Yes, 007.
맞아요
And he also loves to
그리고 연구비도
squeeze the student's allowance.
잘 안 준대
Do you know how much money
거기 박사생
he pays for his doctors every month?
한 달에 얼마 받는지 알아?
Do you know?
아세요?
200 yuan.
200위안
Yes, 200 yuan.
200위안이래
So many doctors
그래서 더 이상 못 버티겠다는
can't stand it anymore.
박사생들이 너무 많아
They are in the sixth year of their doctorate.
6학년인데
Their pressure is too much,
스트레스 너무 많이 받아서
so their hair falls out by the handful.
머리가 다 빠졌대
Sorry, Senior,
죄송합니다, 선배
I didn't mean you.
선배를 말한 게 아니에요
It doesn’t matter.
괜찮아
So they're all posting together
그래서 지금 인터넷에
on the Internet now.
청원 올라오고 있어
Really?
설마
I met Prof. Jiang before,
나 장 교수님 본 적 있어
and he seemed kind,
좋은 분 같던데
could he be such a person?
그럴 사람 같아 보이진 않았어
You still don't believe me?
안 믿는 거야?
See for yourself.
봐봐
Really?
이게 말이 돼?
Don't doubt, that’s true.
왜 말이 안 돼?
Fortunately, last time you didn’t transfer to his lab.
저번에 안 옮기길 잘했어
Otherwise, as a small undergraduate,
학부생인 네가
you'd be a sheep in a tiger's mouth,
거기 가는 건
with no bones left.
호랑이굴에 제 발로 찾아가는 거랑 똑같아
That's right.
그러니까
That's what Jiang Songrui is.
장쑹루이는 원래 그런 사람이야
When you told me that
그때 네가 장 교수님
you were going to his lab,
실험실에 간다고 했을 때
I didn't react.
나도 미처 생각하지 못했는데
If I had,
내가 그때 알았으면
I wouldn't have let you go.
절대 못 가게 말렸지
Right?
안 그래?
Later when Yuhe
그러다 위허가
knew about it,
그 일을 알고
so he immediately stopped you.
가지 말라고 말렸잖아
But,
그런데
you two got into a fight.
두 사람이 또 그 일로
So bad.
싸우게 될 줄이야
Wait.
잠깐만요
You mean that
그러니까
Xiao Yuhe was helping me?
샤오위허가 저를 도와준 거예요?
Yes.
맞아
If you don't believe,
못 믿겠으면
you can ask
위허랑 자오이란한테
Yuhe and Zhao Yiran.
물어봐
They've both worked with Jiang Songrui,
그들도 장쑹루이랑 일해 본 적 있어서
and they know him pretty well.
잘 알 거야
Right, Yiran?
안 그래? 자오이란
Take it.
있어 봐
Chengcheng’s friend,
친구
have some potato chips.
감자칩 먹어
No need.
괜찮아요
Senior, I’ll leave first.
전 먼저 가볼게요
Okay.
그래
Share the gossip next time.
다음에 재밌는 일 있으면 또 말할게요
Come and play often!
자주 놀러 와
Senior.
선배
Zhao Yiran!
자오이란
You heard
아까 한 말
what we just said, right?
다 들었죠?
I've always
전 선배를
thought of you as a good senior.
좋은 사람이라고 생각했는데
Why did you do that?
왜 그랬어요?
You...what do you mean?
그게 무슨 말이야?
I saw you had no place to go,
네가 갈 곳 없으니까
so I wanted to help you with good intentions.
도와주고 싶어서 그런 건데
Besides,
장 교수님이
how could I know that Prof. Jiang
그런 사람인지
has problems?
나도 몰랐지
Didn't you know that?
정말 몰랐어요?
I...
나...
That's it this time.
이번엔 이렇게 넘어갈게요
Next time, you'd better not let me know.
다음엔 들키지 마세요
Otherwise I will...
안 그러면...
Otherwise, what can you do?
안 그러면 어쩔 건데?
Recently, Xixi seems
시시 선배가 곧
to have participated in a boxing competition.
권투 시합에 나갈 건데
She may need someone to practice with.
같이 연습할 사람이 필요할 거예요
You can go.
선배가 가서 하는 건 어때요?
I’ve gotten the reviewers' comments.
심사 의견 나왔어
Many of these comments are things
이 중에
I've already
대부분은
mentioned before!
내가 전에도 강조했던 거야
Have they all been corrected?
수정 안 했어?
Who?
누구야?
What sound?
무슨 소리야?
It sounds like
생쥐가
a mouse eating potato chips.
감자칩을 먹는 소리 같아요
Who’s so bored?
누가 이렇게 한가해?
Have nothing to do?
할 일이 없어서
Then why did you feed the mouse chips?
생쥐한테 감자칩을 먹이는 거야?
No one fed it that.
저희가 먹인 게 아니에요
So you mean that
그럼 생쥐가
the mouse opened its cage
실험 끝나고
after the experiment,
스스로 우리를 열고 나와서는
and went to the supermarket and scanned a QR code
마트에 가서 큐알 코드를 찍고
to buy a packet of potato chips?
감자칩을 샀다는 거야?
Of course not, Prof. Du.
아닙니다, 두 교수님
Because...
사실...
Catch it!
얼른 잡아
I'm coming, I'm coming.
제가 할게요
Go.
저리 가
This side.
이쪽
There, there, there.
저기, 저기
Run that way!
저쪽으로 도망갔어
It's gone. It's gone.
도망갔어
♫Like falling into the bottomless ocean♫
♫ 마치 바다에 빠진 것처럼 깊어 ♫
It's in the...lab.
실험실에 들어갔어
I'm coming! I'm coming!
내가 가서 잡을게
I've got it!
제가 잡았어요
Great!
대단하네
I caught it myself.
제가 생쥐를
Little mouse.
잡았어요
Am I good?
대단하죠?
Senior,
선배
you helped me
저 생각해서
by not letting me
장 교수님의 실험실에
transfer to Prof. Jiang's lab?
가지 말라고 한 거죠?
Don't think too much.
오해하지 마
I did it for a reason.
다 이유가 있었어
Because you
네가 우리 실험실의
have participated in our lab's
중요한 프로젝트에
important projects,
참가한 적 있으니까
I'm afraid...
네가...
You are afraid that I will disclose the content of the research,
제가 연구 결과를 유출할까 봐
so
다른 실험실에
you don't want me to go to another lab?
가지 못하게 한 거예요?
Yes.
맞아
That's a poor excuse.
이유도 그럴싸한 걸로 말해야지
No button for coffee?
커피 마시는데 버튼 안 눌러요?
I don’t drink!
안 마실래
Senior Xixi, are you eating?
선배, 식사하러 왔어요?
Otherwise?
안 그러면?
Other...
안...
Other...otherwise,
안 그러면...
I'll go to get some more food.
제가 밥 좀 더 받아 올게요
Senior Xixi,
시시 선배
here is the juice I bought for you just now.
이건 제가 직접 만든 주스예요
Very tasty.
망고 주스인데
It's mango flavor. Try it.
엄청 맛있어요, 마셔 보세요
What do you want?
무슨 일로 왔어?
I want to say
실험실에 계속
thank you for letting me stay.
있게 해줘서 고마워요
If it weren't for you,
선배가 아니었으면
I'd have to leave.
전 실험실을 나갔을 거예요
And if I had left,
그랬다면 분명
I would have regretted it now.
후회했을 거예요
I want to ask
그래서 말인데
do you have time?
선배 시간 있어요?
If you have time,
시간 괜찮으면
can I invite you to dinner?
제가 밥 한 끼 사도 될까요?
No need to thank me.
고마워할 필요 없어
I'm not the one
널 붙잡으려고 한 건
who wants you to stay.
내가 아니야
Then who is it?
그럼 누구예요?
Who do you think it is?
누구겠어?
With your brain,
너 그 머리로
how did you
우리 실험실엔
get into our lab?
어떻게 들어온 거야?
In order to let you stay, Xiao Yuhe
샤오위허가 널 붙잡으려고
now owes me
나한테 신세를 졌거든
a set of mice facial recognition
그래서 나한테 생쥐 안면 인식을 기반으로 한
automatic feeding system.
셀프 사육 시스템을 만들어 주기로 했어
And he also promised to help Jiang Songrui
그리고 장쑹루이와 같이
to do the project together.
연구 프로젝트도 해야 해
Three labs a day,
하루에 실험실을 세 개씩 드나드는데
he really works hard for you.
걔가 너 때문에 고생이 많네
No way.
말도 안 돼요
How could he help me?
그 사람이 저를 도와줄 리가 없어요
I'm full.
먼저 가볼게
Ask him the rest yourself.
궁금한 건 걔한테 직접 물어봐
Remind you,
하나만 알려줄게
he is
걔는 원래
sometimes like this.
그런 사람이야
What he says is
말과 행동이
the opposite of what he thinks.
다르거든
Did I misunderstand Xiao Yuhe?
내가 샤오위허를 오해한 건가?
He doesn't
그렇게
seem as bad as I think.
나쁜 사람은 아닌 것 같아
I'm getting more and more
정말 알다가도
confused about him.
모를 사람이네